STEPHEN CHARLES

OVERVIEW

Portfolio

Proficient pythonista with a background in mathematics and computer science. Particular expertise in managing software pipelines and large data sets involving time series analysis and machine learning algorithms in addition to interpersual skills from a range of heavitality release.

learning algorithms, in addition to interpersonal skills from a range of hospitality roles.

EMPLOYMENT

2022 - Now

Innovative Technologies – Manchester

Position

Machine Learning Engineer, Placement

STACK

Python, Pytorch, Keras, Tensorflow, Numpy, Pandas, Sklearn, Git, Bash

DUTIES

- ICU performs accurate age verification to automate the policy and allow access to age restricted purchases and premises, through an ensemble of convolutional neural networks.
- With AI algorithms developed over many years, ICU offers an accurate (99.88%) precise and affordable facial recognition system.

2019 - 2020

Facebook (Meta) – London - Remote

Position

Data Scientist, Analytics Intern

STACK

Tableau, SQL, Python

DUTIES

- Performed large-scale data analysis to extract useful business insights.
- Identified the ones which were actionable, suggesting recommendations, and influenced the direction of the business by communicating the results to cross-functional groups.
- Classified leads so that the team could work on the most valuable cases, and suggested improvements in the tools and techniques to help scale the team.

EDUCATION

2021 - 2022 Data Science, University of Bath

MSc Master of Computer Science

Stack

Python, SQL, Pytorch, Keras, Tensorflow, Numpy, Pandas, Sklearn, Matplotlib, Seaborn

Modules

Statistics for Data Science - Probability and statistics, with a focus on translating real-world problems into a mathematical framework in data science contexts.

Machine Learning - Covered both supervised and unsupervised machine learning algorithms from Bishop, including how to develop, evaluate and deploy trained models. The second semester involved advanced techniques focused on neural networks with both regression and classification.

Reinforcement Learning - Implemented various agents to solve environments from Sutton &

Barto, including Dynamic Programming and Temporal Difference methods.

Bayesian Machine Learning - Employing approaches such as inference and monte carlo.

2020 - 2021

Astronomy and Astrophysics, University of Manchester

MSc Distinction, Master of Physics

STACK Python, Numpy, Pandas, Sklearn, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Git, Bash

RESEARCH Published a program to facilitate the data acquisition and analysis pipeline for TESS automatically, dubbed firefly (the best Sci-fi show!), which applies nested sampling (dynesty) to find best fit

variables (TransitFit) between the host star and exoplanet.

2016 - 2020 Mathematics with Computer Science, University of Nottingham

MMATH Upper Second-Class Honours, Master of Mathematics

 ${\tt STACK} \quad \textit{C++, Python, R, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn}$

RESEARCH Dissertation involved working with python to numerically solve spherical cavitation bubble collapse.

2014 - 2016 Space Engineering, Loughborough College

A-Levels Mathematics $A^* \cdot Further\ Mathematics\ A \cdot Physics\ A \cdot Engineering\ A$

A specialised course focused on Engineering with guest lectures at the Space Centre in Leicester.

GENERAL TECH STACK

AWARDS AND QUALIFICATIONS

Language	Python, C++, IATEX, SQL	2022	
PACKAGES	Numpy, Pandas, SciPy, AstroPy	$\boldsymbol{2021}$	Kaggle Expert
ML PACKAGES	Sklearn, Tensorflow, PyTorch	2020	Tableau Desktop Specialist
W_{EB}	HTML, Markdown, CSS	2016	Full UK Driving Licence
SCIENTIFIC	Matlab, R, Fortran, Mathematica	$\boldsymbol{2015}$	Grade 8 Violin
SOFTWARE	Microsoft Office, Tableau, Blender		

PUBLICATIONS

Author

Co-Author

Hayes, J J C, E Kerins, J S Morgan et al. (2021) "TransitFit: an exoplanet transit fitting package for multi-telescope datasets and its application to WASP-127 b, WASP-91 b, and WASP-126 b", 1–14.

ACADEMIC WORK EXPERIENCE

Scholarship, National University of Singapore **AUTUMN 2018**

SCHOLARSHIP Obtained a scholarship to study a crash course in Korean language for 5 weeks and to learn about

the culture and history of the changing landscapes of Singapore. Upon completion, applied to spend

the Autumn semester here successfully.

Physics Outreach, The University of Nottingham July 2017

I began, on a voluntary basis, promoting physics via social media which eventually evolved into a OUTREACH

paid role in which I mediated with events staff in the department to ensure successful participation.

Part of the role was ensuring inclusivity, and how best to target minority groups.

July 2014 Research Intern, Space Research Centre, The University of Leicester

Intern During my first college year I gained work experience at the University of Leicester Space Research

Centre, assisting in the development of an astrobiology rock-sampling tool called SPLIT for use on

Mars.

Positions and Responsibilities

2018 - 2019 Mature Student Mentor, UoN

> I was a point of contact for mature students, helping them settle, and be there in a support capacity.

2017 - 2018

I presented, and gave advice to

prospective students.

PUBLIC SPEAKING

Department of Physics, The University of Nottingham 2017

Gave introductions to guest speakers and shout outs in lectures to ensure everyone was informed of

important events.

2014 Space Research Centre, The University of Leicester

> Presented my findings to a crowd of 50 post doc students and an astronaut! My presentation was based on exoplanet research and the feasibility of alien civilizations to be space faring.

Volunteering

Magical Maths - Nottingham 2017

Role Organisation of weekly sessions to promote mathematics to primary school children, in line with

the national curriculum.

INTERESTS

Avid adventurer and keen

astronomer. This hobby pushes the

Music GENERAL

Self taught Guitar, Piano, Violin. Science fiction and anything spacey.

boundaries of my interest in both.

HIKING

me feel alive.

Surviving extreme conditions makes

References

Dr. Eamonn Kerins NAME TITLE Senior Lecturer

EMAIL

University of Manchester Department of Physics

Prof. Chris Harris Research Professor University of Southampton Dr. John Holt Research Engineer University of Leicester Department of Physics

Fellow

34a Great Whyte Ramsey Cambridgeshire PE26 1HA United Kingdom

Reference: Machine Learning Engineer

Date: Tuesday 22nd March, 2022

Dear Natural History Museum,

Before I started academic study I used to run a server for Ultima Online, primarily written in C++. As such, the server was highly customisable, and with the source code from another server I painfully merged two incompatible SVN's together to create one. Just by comparison alone I was able to get used to the logic and constructs that formed the language. Browsing through the many lines of code and merging was a very slow process, but it allowed me understand slightly different methods of doing things. It was almost like learning through reverse engineering. I like to follow the concept of learning by doing. Of note, I took interest in the AI constructs and pathing algorithms adopted, to try and create realistic npcs to fill the world.

My undergraduate studies primarily focused on Mathematics in its purest form, to which I supplemented this by taking extra modules from physics to practice its application. In my final year I took a formal C++ course to take what I had learned from my game server days and apply it to my reading during undergraduate study. Suddenly very nasty equations were efficiently solved! I think data analysis in this aspect fascinates me. My dissertation project involved the inter-facial perturbations of a spherical bubble, to which an approximate formula was derived. As with most fluid dynamics problems, the solution required numerical analysis. I was able to apply my previous knowledge and reverse engineering, adapting to new problems, using the many libraries and pseudo code available in literature.

Astrophysics became my next programming achievement. Extreme care, and background knowledge was required in the handling and use of very large data sets. The precise information needed extracting and filtering, by which a human doing such by hand would be very laborious! Specifically, I worked in exoplanet research, fitting light curves to improve on the planets already proven to exist. The hope is that with a greater sensitivity, more interesting and varied data will provide confirmation of exomoons and through transit timing variations, more planets! In this field I have written a self-contained python EDA pipeline (firefly) for a transit fitting program (TransitFit) to automate the data collection it requires to run. This was written in python, which has quickly become my favourite language. It can currently fit TESS lightcurves with a nested sampling routine, using a Bayesian machine learning approach. In the future I hope to expand the functionality by allowing simultaneous fitting of multiple space based and ground based telescopes.

I'm keen to apply to the position of Machine Learning Engineer at Natural History Museum because I feel that my past experience would be an asset to your team. My technical background paired with your current expertise would be of great benefit to us both, and I feel that at Natural History Museum I would meet like minded individuals who share the same passions for Data Science.

I am hopeful these considerations will be of benefit in the application process. Should you require more depth than supplied here, please visit my <code>GitHub</code> and <code>Portfolio</code>.

Kind Regards,

Stephen Charles
Stephen Charles